Guide to the Alvin T. Parnell photographs of Durham, North Carolina, circa 1898-1986, bulk 1910-1960 RL.11373
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Alvin T. Parnell photographs of Durham, North Carolina
circa 1898-1986
bulk 1910-1960
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Parnell, Alvin T.
RL.11373
1.5 Linear Feet 2 boxes; 183 items
Alvin T. Parnell was a commercial photographer based in Durham, N.C. Collection chiefly consists of 167 black-and-white photographs of the city and people of Durham, North Carolina. The majority, chiefly taken by Parnell from 1920 through the 1950s, are views of downtown streets, commercial and industrial buildings, churches, and infrastructure, especially transportation. Many sites are related to the tobacco manufacturing businesses based in Durham. A few are of African American tobacco workers posed in the field and female factory workers ending their shift. Other images range widely and include a Trinity College (later Duke University) reunion, war veterans at gatherings, a minstrel band, a cart advertising Bull Durham tobacco, and tobacco fields with posed workers, white and African American. In addition, there are portraits of prominent Durham individuals and families. Formats include 85 vintage and modern gelatin silver prints, chiefly 8x10 inches, 82 contact prints, and 12 safety negatives. Includes an information folder with 1986 obituary and collection information.
2 boxes; 183 items
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: Photographs, Contact Prints, and Negatives. The photographs are arranged in three groupings: places, people, and a few miscellaneous images; and in rough chronological order within.
Biographical / Historical
Alvin Talmadge Parnell (1899-1986) was born in Horry County, South Carolina. He became an apprentice in the Walter Holladay photography studio in Durham, N.C., located on Main Street (often spelled Halladay or Holloday). When he returned from World War I service, he took over the Holladay studio from a Mr. Ramsey, and operated it under his name until the 1950s, when he left Durham to live in Lumberton, N.C. His wife took over the business, renaming it the Overton-Parnell Studio. It is likely that in addition to providing photographs for business clients, Parnell also acted as photographer for Durham City Hall, the Chamber of Commerce, and local newspapers. Parnell died in 1986 and is buried in Lumberton.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Original negatives are closed to general use; access only by permission of the Archive of Documentary Arts Curator. Viewing copies may be made for access to content.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Alvin T. Parnell photographs of Durham, North Carolina were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1975.
Related Materials
Durham Chamber of Commerce records, circa 1910-1981 (photographs from Holladay Studio and probably by Alvin Parnell)
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Content Description
Collection comprises 167 early to mid-20th century black-and-white photographs of the city and people of Durham, North Carolina. The majority of the images were taken by Alvin T. Parnell, a commercial photographer with a studio in downtown Durham, from about 1920 to 1950; prints from 1898 to 1919 likely were from the Cole-Holladay studio, which Parnell took over around 1920. Formats include a few vintage mounted albumen and gelatin silver prints, unmounted vintage and modern gelatin silver prints, and small contact prints made from original nitrate negatives. There are also twelve safety film negatives present, from which some copy prints were made. Includes an information folder with Parnell's 1986 obituary and collection information.
The largest group of photographs, taken from the late 1910s through the early 1950s, features views of Durham's growing downtown, often commissioned by Parnell's business and City Hall clients. In the background of the many street scenes one can see the progression of small storefront businesses that made up life on Main Street in a 20th century Southern Piedmont city. Given Durham's role as a birthplace for the post-Civil War tobacco manufacturing industry, it is not surprising that there are numerous photographs of buildings and industrial sites belonging to American Tobacco, Blackwell Tobacco, and Liggett Myers. Parnell also photographed buses, trolleys, and other scenes for an early Durham power and transportation company, Durham Public Services.
Other images focus on people, and range widely in subject matter: men posed at a Trinity College (later Duke University) reunion, war veterans at gatherings, fraternities, children on a playground, and a minstrel band. A few are of African American tobacco workers posed in the field and female factory workers ending their shift. There are also portraits of prominent individuals and families: an elderly Bennehan Cameron with family members; John Ruffin Green (one of Durham's earliest tobacco entrepreneurs); Washington Duke and sons with associates at a barbeque; the Rosenstein family (optometrists from New York who came to Durham in 1904); William Umstead (U.S. Senator from northern Durham County); and various police chiefs and businessmen. There are also a few portraits of women, some with captions and some unidentified.
There are also twelve safety film negatives in the collection, sized 8x10 and 4x5 inches, from which a selection of copy prints were made after the collection was acquired. A few have no existing prints – these are noted in the collection guide.
In addition to photographs in this collection, some if not most of the earlier images of Durham in the Durham Chamber of Commerce collection in the Rubenstein Library are likely to have been taken by Parnell. His work is also likely to be found in other collections related to Durham residents containing photographs.
Separated Materials
After contact prints were made at acquisition, nitrate negatives were discarded.
Central business districts -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Pictorial works; City and town life -- Durham, N.C. -- Pictorial works; Commercial photography -- North Carolina -- Durham; Photographers -- North Carolina -- Durham; Tobacco industry -- North Carolina -- History; Durham (N.C.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works; Durham (N.C.) -- Economic conditions; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Durham (N.C.) -- Pictorial works; Durham (N.C.) -- Social life and customs; Durham County (N.C.) -- History; North Carolina -- History; Albumen prints; Black-and-white photographs; Contact prints; Gelatin silver prints; Negatives (photographs); Parnell, Alvin T.
- Photographs, circa 1898-1950s; 1; 85 items
  Scope and Contents
  Eight-five photographs make up the series, all black-and-white gelatin silver prints ranging in size from about 4x5 to 8x10 inches, with the great majority in the latter size category. There are also three larger prints roughly 11x14 inches. About a third are vintage prints, with the rest being modern copy prints made from negatives or contact prints. Many thus have a corresponding duplicate in the contact prints series, and though smaller, some contacts offer lighter, clearer images. There are a number of contact prints whose images are not found in the Photographs series. There are also images present in the Negatives series without a corresponding positive print in the collection.
  Because Parnell took over the Cole-Holladay studio around 1919 or 1920, there are some pre-1919 prints that originated from Holladay; prints taken after 1920 were the Parnell studio's work. Credit for the Bennett place photograph has been given by the Library of Congress to a John Chapman Michie; it is not known how the print came to be in the Parnell's collection.
  Written on the backs of the vintage prints are various captions and other remarks in Parnell's hand, and sometimes reproduction and layout markings, probably for use in the local newspaper. A few are signed by Parnell, or marked with his studio stamp.
  The prints are in numerical order as assigned by library staff, in rough chronological order within subseries. Descriptions of subject content are found in the subseries notes and individual entries for each photograph.
  Arrangement
  Prints were formerly in random order; they have been organized into three series: Places, Transportation, People, and Other.
  - Places, circa 1910-1950s; 2; 47 items
    These 47 images begin with one of the city of Durham's earliest sites, with the Bennitt farmstead - site of the largest Civil War surrender - photographed around 1904. Subsequent images chiefly document the 1910s and 1920s, as Durham grew into a busy manufacturing center based almost exclusively on the tobacco industry.
    Because of Alvin Parnell's preference for outdoor work and his many commissions from city merchants, the photographs capture in great detail downtown development, doucmenting nearly every major commercial landmark and church in the town, as well as some of its most significant residences. Along the way, Parnell's lens also documented the passersby, traffic, storefronts, and advertising of those early decades.
    All of the images are in black-and-white, and about half are modern copy prints made sometime in the 1980s from the original negatives or contact prints. The rest are vintage gelatin silver prints. When Parnell took over the Cole-Holladay studio around 1919 or 1920, following his World War I service, he inherited some pre-1919 prints that originated from the earlier studio (where he was also apprenticed before 1919).
    - Bennett [Bennitt] farm buildings and tree, Hillsborough Road, original image by John Chapman Michie (?), circa 1904 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0001)
      These buildings were gone by 1921. On back of print: "Parnell Studio, Al. Parnell, Photographer, 209 1/2 W. Main St...copyright secured." Library of Congress copy negative catalog record gives photographer's name as John Chapman Michie, circa 1904.
    - Durham Loan and Trust building, W. Main St., before 1910 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0002)
      Electricity poles present in a 1910 photograph of Trust Building and new Post Office are absent in this image. One of two copies.
    - Durham Loan and Trust building, W. Main St., before 1910 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0003)
      Duplicate.
    - Temple Building, 302 W. Main St., headquarters for Home Savings Loan, Elks, and Odd Fellows, circa 1916 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0004)
    - Four Acres, Benjamin N. Duke's residence, seen from the rear, circa 1920 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0005)
    - Trinity Church, downtown Durham, before 1923 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0006)
      Building burned in January 1923.
    - Bennett Place, Hillsborough Road, before 1923 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0007)
      Commemoration or other ceremony, with a large crowd; a single surviving chimney of Bennett farm is visible in background. A columned memorial was erected on the site in 1923.
    - Bennett Place Unity monument, Hillsborough Road, after 1923 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0008)
      Memorial to Civil War surrender was erected in 1923.
    - Bennett Place Unity monument, Hillsborough Road, after 1923 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0009)
    - Five Points Drug Co., front view, with men informally posed in front, 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0010)
    - Five Points Drug Co., 1920s (duplicate, reversed) (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0011)
    - Five Points Drug Co., 1920s (duplicate, reversed) (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0012)
    - Five Points Drug Co., 1920s, enlargement (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0013)
      Enlargement showing detail of front of building.
    - Central downtown, 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0014)
    - Jordan Building, West Main St., with Sears Roebuck, Rosenstein's clothing, and Lipscomb-Gattis, 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0015)
    - Masonic Building, later known as Eligibility Building, East Main St., after 1924 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0016)
      Housed several organizations, including Elks and Freemasons.
    - Downtown, white men in suits and African American workers standing on truck behind brick buildings, with pile of cartons on ground marked "Chesterfield," circa 1920 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0017)
    - Paschall Bakery buildings, Duke and Morgan Sts., after 1924 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0018)
    - Bull-drawn wagon at curbside, hung with advertising placards, and announcement of "Man Buried Alive" show for "Benefit Community Relief Committee," circa 1920 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0019)
      Original print.
    - Bull-drawn wagon at curbside, hung with advertising placards, and announcement of "Man Buried Alive" show for "Benefit Community Relief Committee," circa 1920 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0020)
      Modern copy print.
    - Jourdan Transfer Company trucks and African American and white workers, back of buildings on Main St. (?), circa 1920 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0021)
    - West Main St. (?), 100 block, with Jourdan Transfer Company, 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0022)
    - Hackney Block buildings, with Plaza Café and drugstore, 1925 April 5 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0023)
      Date from paper slip.
    - West Main St., with Whelan Drugstore, Tipton's, late 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0024)
    - Durham Ice Cream building, Duke Street (?), 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0025)
      "Durham Ice Cream" written on back of print.
    - The Salvation Army Citadel, Morris St., early 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0026)
      Information from paper slip.
    - H. M Kramer Tobacco Company Wholesale, Holland St., 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0027)
      Now Holland Alley.
    - Durham County Courthouse, second iteration, E. Main St., early 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0028)
    - E.H. and M.V. Wholesale Millers building on fire, Peabody St., after 1924 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0029)
    - Corner of Hunt and Mangum Streets, 1928 January 20 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0030)
    - Durham Morning Herald buildings, Market St., probably 1929 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0031)
      The Durham Morning Herald acquired the Durham Sun in 1929. The buildings were demolished in 1930.
    - Unidentified Art Deco building, Main St. (?), with Christmas light decorations, 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0032)
    - Two Lakewood/Mangum Streets buses stop for passengers on W. Main St., looking west, with Salvation Army and Elliott Furniture Company buildings in background, circa 1920 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0033)
      Note poster advertising a Charlie Chaplin movie. Print is very dark; contact print offers a lighter, clearer image.
    - Garage, power plant, downtown, unknown street, circa 1920 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0034)
      Dark print; contact print, if present in collection, may be clearer.
    - Old-style stoplight and directional signs for cities, unknown intersection, circa 1920 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0035)
    - Aerial view of large complex of low tobacco warehouses, Broad St. Extension, with farms surrounding it and Durham in distance, circa late 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0036)
    - Unidentified large one-story warehouse, with long line of chauffeurs and cars waiting in front, late 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0037)
      May be warehouse complex on Broad St. Extension, north Durham.
    - Unidentified large brick building, Durham, with ivy on it, 1926? (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0038)
      On back of print: "Holladay 26."
    - Beavers and Montgomery Standard Oil service station with tiled roof, Mangum and Chapel Hill Sts., 1925 July 25 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0039)
    - Standard Oil service station with tiled roof, from further away, with "--Ty Transfer Co.," and "Happy Feed Store," unknown location in Durham, 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0040)
    - Carolina Theater (Durham Auditorium), Morgan St., 1930 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0041)
    - Aerial view of Four Acres, Duke Memorial Methodist Church, West Chapel Hill St., 1930s? (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0042)
    - Fayetteville St. bus stopped at the Liggett and Myers factory at a shift change, women workers and Fire Station #2 are visible, circa 1930 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0043)
    - Lucky Strike tower and American Tobacco complex, additional construction completion, circa 1930 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0044)
    - Looking west-northwest down Seminary St. towards the Roycroft Warehouse tobacco auction complex on Rigsbee, 1940s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0045)
    - Durham aerial view by Charles Doherty of Greensboro, 1930s? (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0046)
    - Durham aerial view, 1930s? (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0047)
    - Durham County Courthouse, second iteration, E. Main St., early 1920s (Box 2, Image RL-11373-P-0086)
      Larger, lighter version of smaller print in collection, sized 9 1/4 x 11 3/4 inches.
    - View of Durham downtown, looking south, 1920s (Box 2, Image RL-11373-P-0087)
      Visible in background are the American Tobacco complex and the Blackwell Old Bull building. On back of print: "looking S by E from hotel / Uptown [banking?] district." 9 1/4 x 12 1/2 inches.
  - Transportation, 1920s; 3; 11 items
    Parnell received a commission from an early Durham utility and transportation company, Durham Public Services (DPS), to photograph their fleets of vehicles and city power and transportation infrastructure. Thus, these 11 images chiefly show DPS trolleys, ice trucks, and buses parked at the car barn and on city streets. A few include people: conductors and DPS officials posing by a bus, and passengers getting on or off a trolley. One image is of the Gulf Refining Company property in 1925, with a group of three tanker trucks. Another 1920s photograph is of Durham's Alexander Motor Company's display of new Ford models at a trade show.
    - Durham Public Service work truck No. 3 on an unpaved city street, late 1910s or early 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0048)
    - Hospital and Country Club trolley car near car barn, E. Main St., before 1930 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0049)
    - Close-up of Hospital and Country Club trolley car near car barn, E. Main St., before 1930 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0050)
    - Hope Valley line bus with conductors and men in suits posing in front, Five Points/Main St., late 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0051)
      Second-story shops visible in background: C.D. Kenny Co., Warrenetta Hair Shop; Durham Art Shop; Bluefield Coal and Coke Co.
    - City trolley with advertisement for a show at City Auditorium, picking up passengers, unknown location, 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0052)
      One of two copies. Very dark prints; contact print offers a lighter and clearer image.
    - City trolley with advertisement for a show at City Auditorium, picking up passengers, unknown location, 1920s (duplicate) (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0053)
    - Line of eight Durham Public Service buses, seen from front angle, parked on East Main with Carpenter Motor Co. in background, late 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0054)
    - Line of eight Durham Public Service buses, seen from rear angle, parked on East Main, late 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0055)
    - Lakewood Park bus, parked on side of wide street, unknown location, late 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0056)
    - Gulf Refining Company, three tanker trucks parked in industrial location, water tower in distance, 1925 May 30 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0057)
    - Alexander Motor Company, Ford automobile showcase at trade show or fair, circa 1920 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0084)
      Printed on heavy fabric-backed photographic paper.
  - People, circa 1898-1940s; 4; 25 items
    The earliest photograph in the collection is housed in this series; taken in 1898, it shows a group of young women belonging to the Trinity Church Sunday School class. After another early image of prominent citizen Julian Shakespeare Carr reviewing Confederate veterans in front of the Carrolina Hotel, circa 1903, the rest of the photographs date chiefly from the 1920s through the 1940s, and show Durham citizens in both casual and posed settings.
    Subjects range widely, and include: children playing in an early playground field across from two tobacco warehouses; the dark interior of a bank with customer and tellers; two scenes from a Trinity College reunion; a large musical band advertising a minstrel show, a group of World War I veterans; and portraits of Bennehan Cameron as an elderly man, John Ruffin Green (one of Durham's earliest tobacco entrepreneurs), the Rosenstein family (early Durham optometrists), and several men affiliated with the Durham Police Department. Some are photographs of portraits. Only a few individuals are unidentified.
    Two of the photographs are film or television stills: one was labeled as a scene from the 1925 movie "Durham's Hero," filmed in the city (there are several contact prints from this same movie), and one is from an unidentified set featuring a scene in a Mexican-style cantina from about the early 1940s.
    - Trinity Church Sunday School class, circa 1898 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0058)
      All young women; names include: Whitaker, Bradsher, Ella Peay, Daisy Cox, Mary Cole. Albumen on card mount.
    - Julian Carr reviewing his Confederate regiment in front of Carolina Hotel, circa 1903, 4 items (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0059)
      Three modern copies. Original is in Durham Chamber of Commerce collection.
    - Children on playground field across from two tobacco warehouses, circa 1920 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0060)
      Stamped on photo: "Halladay Studio, Durham N.C." (Holladay is mis-spelled.)
    - Portrait of Abraham Rosenstein and family, early optometrist, circa 1920 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0061)
      Information from caption on back of print: 25th wedding anniversary photo of Mr. and Mrs. Rosenstein, with four children, left to right: Florence, Ricky Ray, Eva, and Abraham Jr.
    - Interior of bank [?], with male customer and two female tellers, 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0062)
      Bank manager can be seen in background through open office door.
    - Large "Traveling Men's Minstrel Band," posed in front of Shepherd Furniture Co. in downtown Durham, 1922 April 17 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0063)
      Screatched into negative is "Parnell, Durham, NC, 4-17-22."
    - Portrait of Bennehan Cameron (d. 1925), with three others, likely daughter and son-in-laws, early 1920s (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0064)
    - Eleven men from Trinity College class of 1896 at a reunion, 1926? (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0065)
    - Trinity College classes of 1901 and 1906 posed in front of sign, "Plaza of Year, Reunion Class Headquarters," 1926? (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0066)
    - Portrait of Duke May Queen Beryl Jones and her attendant, Marie Tyler, 1928 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0067)
      On back of print: "Miss Jones later married Dr. Runyon Tyler of Durham and Miss Tyler, Mr. Lindsey Gudger of Asheville."
    - Dougherty Men's Fraternity, 13 men posted in group, May 10, 1939 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0068)
      On back of print: "May 10 1939, Durham Public Services, Vandiner" [?].
    - [Works Progress Administration?] Posed portrait of group of men in similar khaki-style uniforms, 1930s? (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0069)
      Shirt fronts have stamped letters "W," "P," and perhaps an "A," in various combinations.
    - Portrait of William Umstead (1895-1954), U.S. Senator from Bahama, 1930s? (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0070)
    - Portrait of man reportedly affiliated with Police Department, "Dillard," 1930s? (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0071)
    - Portrait of "Mr. Wilson," man in uniform, reportedly affiliated with Police Department, 1939 (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0072)
      Date and name from back of print.
    - Studio portrait of Charlotte Ford, unretouched proof, damaged, late 1930s? (Box 1, Image RL-11373-P-0073)
      Possibly a high school portrait of daughter of Walter S. Ford, Durham.